<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="pretty-atom-feed.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Dan Munz</title>
  <subtitle>This is a longer description about your blog.</subtitle>
  <link href="https://danmu.nz/feed/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://danmu.nz/" />
  <updated>2025-07-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://danmu.nz/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Dan Munz</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>A ChatGPT historian prompt</title>
    <link href="https://danmu.nz/blog/chat-gpt-historian-prompt/" />
    <updated>2025-07-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://danmu.nz/blog/chat-gpt-historian-prompt/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was futzing around with ChatGPT the other day to see how much info I could get it to cram into a single answer, and started playing with things like &amp;quot;tell me everything that happened in the 20th century minute-by-minute.&amp;quot; That didn&#39;t really get anywhere, but led to a fun prompt that generates a readable account of any historical event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made a &lt;a href=&quot;https://help.openai.com/en/articles/10169521-projects-in-chatgpt&quot;&gt;project folder&lt;/a&gt; called History By The Hour and gave it the instructions below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are a meticulous historical analyst and global news correspondent, with a focus on behind-the-scenes communications and international perspectives. You synthesize official records, news reports, diplomatic cables, and memoirs, always aiming for accuracy, clarity, and a sense of immediacy. Your tone is engaged, objective, and brings in human details (snippets of dialogue, observations about public mood, etc.), helping the reader feel the lived reality of the unfolding events. You occasionally &amp;quot;zoom in&amp;quot; on the events of particular discussions, chances, meetings, moments, etc. that help the reader truly &amp;quot;feel&amp;quot; the enormity of unfolding events.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;You provide context as needed, but keep the narrative tightly anchored to the clock and global vantage point. Your prose style is clear and readable, not flowery or verbose, but with the occasional writerly verb or adjective to help the reader &amp;quot;feel&amp;quot; the relevant events.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;When I ask you about a given historical event or period, give me an hour-by-hour (or, if needed, day-by-day) chronology covering the actions, communications, and reactions of all relevant entities—not just within the main country or actor, but also internationally. Include governments, military, media, and key groups outside the main country, showing how they learned about, discussed, and responded to events. Summarize each hour (or significant hour) with as much detail as available. Only include &#39;no significant event recorded&#39; if the historical record is truly blank for that hour and perspective.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Present the timeline in clear chronological order, labeling times and locations. Highlight diplomatic, military, domestic, and public/media reactions as they happened. Be sure to expand your time frame so that your recap covers the lead-up to and aftermath of the event; I want to learn how people found out about and reacted to it, especially when things were unclear or just forming, not just be plopped into the thick of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I can just start a new chat with &lt;a href=&quot;https://chatgpt.com/share/68693000-9064-8004-ae33-69743e810297&quot;&gt;a simple question like “tell me about the fall of the Berlin Wall”&lt;/a&gt; and get a readable blow-by-blow account. If you (like me) find yourself needing to put down a nonfiction book every three pages to delve into the extensive Wikipedia entry for every new character/place/proper noun that&#39;s introduced, I think this&#39;ll just about fit your attention span.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>WWDC and Apple&#39;s AI device strategy</title>
    <link href="https://danmu.nz/blog/WWDC-Apples-AI-device-strategy/" />
    <updated>2025-06-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://danmu.nz/blog/WWDC-Apples-AI-device-strategy/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Right after WWDC, I was feeling underwhelmed and a little baffled. But with a week of hindsight, I think the commentary was so focused on the aesthetics of Liquid Glass, it missed the function. Liquid Glass tells me that Apple thinks your AI device of the future isn’t a new wearable, but the iPhone you already own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google, OpenAI, and Meta have world-class LLMs, but an LLM isn’t a product until it’s in something you can use. Google and Meta are making glasses. Jony Ive is making a brushed-aluminium…something. They are betting they can cram their models into something new that you’ll wear, talk to, and be seen with in public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple&#39;s current on-device LLM sucks. That’s a big problem, but it’s one they can solve with time and/or some of the $50 billion in cash they’re sitting on. More importantly, it’s the easy part of the AI device problem to solve. The hard part is everything else: materials, battery, screen, supply chain, ecosystem. The stuff the iPhone has already solved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the iPhone is your AI device, it’s going to need a new interface. That&#39;s where Liquid Glass comes in. It&#39;s not aesthetically my cup of tea, but everything about Liquid Glass is designed to merge digital UI and physical context:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can literally see through it. (Welcome back, Frutiger Aero!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It adapts blur and brightness dynamically over depth-of-field images&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Menus unfold in place instead of breaking flow with submenus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Modal-less interfaces get more emphasis and power, letting you take actions without breaking context&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Camera, once a tangle of indistinguishable &amp;quot;modes,&amp;quot; launches with two buttons&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spotlight is a lightweight assistant, not a dumb search bar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is how you prepare the iPhone to be a personal AI device: by getting the UI out of the way. Apple thinks you&#39;ll spend a lot more time simultaneously looking at and through your phone. They want the screen to be a window, not a camera. To me, this is a much more plausible theory than getting people used to glasses or a pin or a glowing pebble on a necklace and solving every attendant hardware and interface challenge from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This may work or it may not. Tim Cook needs to lace up his Nikes and get into the LLM race. But the &amp;quot;Apple is washed up&amp;quot; vibe shift has gone way too far. They already own the hardest part of an AI assistant to get right: the device. The rest is about money and design sense. Magic Mouse charging port aside, Apple&#39;s got a lot of both. Who are you betting on?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(h/t to Tara Tan, whose &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/posts/tantara_today-design-royalty-has-been-dethroned-activity-7337927311045926912-BqFB&quot;&gt;provocative recent post on this&lt;/a&gt; inspired me to get my own thoughts down on pixel.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post was originally &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/posts/danmunz_wwdc-activity-7340717363371143170--Z8o/&quot;&gt;published on LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;. Since then, Apple has indeed &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.is/BXtd4&quot;&gt;started exploring swapping out its own LLM with a competitor&#39;s&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A rocket-powered onion peeler</title>
    <link href="https://danmu.nz/blog/a-rocket-powered-onion-peeler/" />
    <updated>2025-06-11T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://danmu.nz/blog/a-rocket-powered-onion-peeler/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Everyone’s having a good laugh at this image going around Twitter:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/avif&quot; srcset=&quot;https://danmu.nz/blog/a-rocket-powered-onion-peeler/mHhAZe4KTq-960.avif 960w&quot;&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://danmu.nz/blog/a-rocket-powered-onion-peeler/mHhAZe4KTq-960.webp 960w&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://danmu.nz/blog/a-rocket-powered-onion-peeler/mHhAZe4KTq-960.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;960&quot; height=&quot;584&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I think it’s actually a surprisingly useful way of thinking about AI: Not as a technology but as a product methodology. A rocket-powered onion peeler.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go with me here a minute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s an old joke: &amp;quot;How do you carve a statue of an elephant? You start with a block of marble and chisel away everything that doesn’t look like an elephant.&amp;quot; LLMs operate sort of the same way. Instead of starting with a blank page, you start with a block of marble shaped like all-of-human-knowledge and use prompts to chisel away everything that &lt;em&gt;isn’t&lt;/em&gt; what you want. This reframes AI not as a generative method—after all, it&#39;s just other people&#39;s content fed into a bunch of fancy math—but as a tool for winnowing raw material down into the thing you want. Every time you refine a query, you&#39;re chopping a little bit more marble off the block.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this is a useful frame for product thinking, because it’s closer to how product definition often works in the real world: We&#39;re not conjuring features out of thin air, we&#39;re filtering down a big pool of possibilities to land on what actually works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steve Jobs once said:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you first start off trying to solve a problem, the first solutions you come up with are very complex, and most people stop there. But if you keep going, and live with the problem and peel more layers of the onion off, you can often arrive at some very elegant and simple solutions. Most people just don’t put in the time or energy to get there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Great products often come from &lt;em&gt;removing&lt;/em&gt; not adding. Thinking of an LLM as a tool for accelerating that—a rocket-powered onion peeler—lets us start with a much larger corpus of possibilities and whittle more precisely and creatively. Could it replace Agile the way Agile has &amp;quot;replaced&amp;quot; waterfall, or at least sit alongside it? Who knows. But I&#39;d &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; to see someone actually build a delivery methodology around it. Is this a useful idea, or am I just sniffing marble dust?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(For avoidance of doubt, the —es are mine. I was using emdashes long before ChatGPT was.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post was originally &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/posts/danmunz_aiproductdesign-llms-productthinking-activity-7338180639520661504-g1aT/&quot;&gt;published on LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;. Image credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/jxnlco/&quot;&gt;Jason Liu&lt;/a&gt;, @jxnlco on Twitter.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>This is my second post with a much longer title.</title>
    <link href="https://danmu.nz/blog/secondpost/" />
    <updated>2018-07-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://danmu.nz/blog/secondpost/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Leverage agile frameworks to provide a robust synopsis for high level overviews. Iterative approaches to corporate strategy foster collaborative thinking to further the overall value proposition. Organically grow the holistic world view of disruptive innovation via workplace diversity and empowerment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;section-header&quot;&gt;Section Header&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://danmu.nz/blog/firstpost.md&quot;&gt;First post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://danmu.nz/blog/secondpost/blog/thirdpost.md&quot;&gt;Third post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bring to the table win-win survival strategies to ensure proactive domination. At the end of the day, going forward, a new normal that has evolved from generation X is on the runway heading towards a streamlined cloud solution. User generated content in real-time will have multiple touchpoints for offshoring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Capitalize on low hanging fruit to identify a ballpark value added activity to beta test. Override the digital divide with additional clickthroughs from DevOps. Nanotechnology immersion along the information highway will close the loop on focusing solely on the bottom line.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>